Guide to the St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery Records 1796-2019 MS 443.9
New-York Historical Society
St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery records
1796-2019
New-York Historical Society
St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery (New York, N.Y.)
MS 443.9
50 Linear feet in 57 boxes of various sizes.
The collection includes records of St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery from its earliest days at the end of the 18th century and into the early 21st century. The collection is particularly rich in two respects: with administrative and financial records for the 19th century and early 20th century, and with records related to the renovation and restoration of the church building and grounds and of the rectory in the last decades of the 20th century.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 4 series:
Series I. Minute Books, 1799-1937
Series II. Treasurer Records and Related Financial Matters, 1796-1938
Series III. Other Administration Records, 1800-1944
Series IV. Buildings Renovation and Restoration, 1966-2019
Biographical / Historical
St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery is an Episcopalian church located on East 10th Street on the Lower East Side of the borough of Manhattan in New York City. The church is recognized as the oldest site of continuous religious worship in Manhattan, with the location dating back to the site of a chapel built in 1660 by colonial governor Peter Stuyvesant (1612-1672), who is buried in a vault at the church. In 1793, the original chapel was sold to Trinity Church, which initiated construction of a new church building. This fieldstone building was consecrated in 1799 and, with subsequent expansions, still exists today. Also in 1799, St. Mark's Parish was formed, spinning off from Trinity Parish.
Various changes were made to the church building through the 19th century, including the addition of the spire in 1828. Burial vaults were constructed in the yards on either side of the church. The church was designated a New York City landmark in 1966. Rectories were also built, with the third and final one on East 11th Street designed by Ernest O. Flagg and completed in 1900. The reach of the parish also expanded in the 19th century as mission chapels were established at other points in the city, including uptown on 44th Street (later to move to 48th Street and become the center of its own parish) and on East 10th Street and Avenue A (now the St. Nicholas of Myra Orthodox Church).
When the church was founded in 1799, its location was still a rural area on the fringe of the most populous part of New York City. But as the city expanded north, St. Mark's found itself located in what came to be known as the Lower East Side, a dense urban area that underwent many cultural and demographic shifts over the course of a century and more. By the late 1960s, as part of its effort to navigate these changes, St. Mark's established the Preservation Youth Project (PYP), a program aimed at engaging with youth from the community, specifically in terms of construction jobs training as applied to restoration work in the churchyards and then the church building itself. Devastating fires of the church in 1978 and of the rectory in 1988 set these restoration efforts back, though they were ultimately successful. (See the historical note at Series IV of this collection for elaboration on the restoration projects.) Celebrating its rich history and Dutch connections through Peter Stuyvesant, as well as its re-emergence from the 1978 fire, the church welcomed Queen Beatrix of the Netherlands as a visitor in 1982. Reflecting the church's intent to more broadly serve the surrounding community, the restored rectory was repurposed as the Neighborhood Preservation Center available, in part, for community workshops, meetings, and workspaces.
(The above note was based on various on-line sources, including the websites of St. Marks' Church and the New York Preservation Archive, as well as documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers, with the exception of certain personnel-related records noted in the container list that are restricted pending further curatorial review.
Much of the material is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was donated over time by St. Mark's Church:
* Most of the treasurer records found in Series II were donated on April 15, 1940.
* An addition to the treasurer records was donated on August 2, 1967.
* That 1967 donation also included most of the various other documents in the collection that range from the 19th century into the mid-20th century.
* There is some indication that the draft minutes of 1839-44 found in Series I were donated in December 1963.
* One box of 19th century documents apparently was purchased by N-YHS in 1972 from Gilman's rare book store.
* The records ranging from the late 20th century to 2019 that are related to the preservation and renovation of the church and rectory (Series IV) were donated on May 7, 2021.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes records of St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery from its earliest days at the end of the 18th century and into the early 21st century. The collection is particularly rich in two respects: with administrative and financial records for the 19th century and early 20th century, and with records related to the renovation and restoration of the church building and grounds and of the rectory in the last decades of the 20th century.
The collection holds a complete run of the vestry minute books from 1799 to 1937; extensive financial records through the 19th century and into the 1910s, including the treasurer account books for 1860-1907; and other 19th century records, including pew rentals, property leases, some correspondence, and other matters.
The collection holds relatively few records from the mid-20th century, especially so for the late-1940s and into the late 1960s. The largest part of the collection, however, ranges from the late 1960s and to 2019, and centers on the church and rectory restoration projects, both those preceding and subsequent to the devastating fires of 1978 (the church) and 1988 (the rectory). These records concern the Preservation Youth Project (PYP), which performed much of the restoration work; the fundraising for the PYP and the restoration projects; management of the St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund, which was formed in 1979 in part as a vehicle for managing the restoration funds; and the repurposing and management of the restored rectory, opening as the Neighborhood Preservation Center (NPC) in 1999. These records include financial information (budgets, grant proposals, progress reports, account statements, etc.); project concept and planning documents; supplier/contractor estimates and proposals; Landmark Fund and NPC management records (Fund trustee minutes, NPC advisory committee minutes); photographs (of the PYP at work, the fire-damaged buildings, events, etc.); publicity, solicitation materials, and historical surveys; and more.
Related Materials
N-YHS holds several other documents related to St. Mark's Church, including the legal opinion signed by Alexander Hamilton and others regarding the proposed transfer of land from Trinity Church to St. Mark's. A search of Bobcat with the church name will identify these items.
N-YHS also holds various images in various formats of St. Mark's, especially in its Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections (PPAC). These can be identified through a search in the library's finding aid full text search site.
Checks (bank checks); Church records.; Financial records.; Leases.; Letters (correspondence); Marriage records.; Membership lists.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Church history.; Church buildings -- Reconstruction.; Church finance -- New York (State) -- New York.; Church work with youth -- New York (State) -- New York.; Episcopalians -- New York (State) -- New York.; Fund raising -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic preservation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Parsonages -- Remodeling for other use -- New York (State) -- New York.; Pews and pew rights -- New York (State) -- New York.; Episcopal Church. Diocese of New York.; Neighborhood Preservation Center (New York, N.Y.); St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery (New York, N.Y.). Preservation Youth Project.; St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund.
- Series I. Minute Books, 1799-1937; 1.21 Linear feet in 5 shelved volumes + 1 box
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes several volumes of minutes for meetings of the vestry, rector, and church wardens, spanning 1793-1937, along with some rough draft minutes. There are also some minutes for the Ladies Benevolent Society of St. Mark's, which helped the poor in the parish, contributed clothing to missionaries and soldiers, and made and sold clothing for benefit of the poor.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged by document type/subject.
  - Minutes of the Vestry, 1799-1861 March (Volume 1)
  - Minutes of the Vestry, 1861 April-1899 April (Volume 2)
  - Minutes of the Vestry, 1899 May-1931 April (Volume 3)
  - Minutes of the Vestry, 1931 April-1933 April (Volume 4)
  - Minutes of the Vestry, 1933 April-1937 October (Volume 5)
  - "Rough" (draft) minutes, 1839 May-1844 March (Box 1)
    Additional rough minute notes from this period can be found in box 13.
  - Minutes. Ladies Benevolent Society of St. Mark's, 1861 December-1864 April (Box 1)
  - Minutes. Ladies Benevolent Society of St. Mark's, 1875 November-1883 April (Box 1)
- Series II. Treasurer Records and Related Financial Matters, 1796-1938; 4.2 Linear feet in 10 document boxes + 1 shelved volume
  The series includes an extensive set of records of financial transactions from the 19th century into the early 20th century. Box/folder content labeled as "Financial matters" includes invoices, receipts, business transaction correspondence, treasurer's statements, and other such documents. These folders also include some documents regarding non-financial matters. The series includes records of properties leased by the church, pew rentals, offerings, and other sources of revenue. Insurance policies, cancelled checks, tax statements, and other such documents are in the series, though there are relatively few of these and none make up a consistent run.
  The series is arranged with the general financial records first, proceeding in chronological order, followed by various other specific types of accounting and financial records and documents, as listed in the container list.
  - Financial matters (7 folders), 1803-1849 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
    One topic among many touched in these folders concerns music for the church and the related acquisition of an organ and services of an organist.
  - Financial matters (10 folders), 1850-1864 (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
  - Financial matters (12 folders), 1865-1879 (Box 4, Folder 1-12)
  - Financial matters (7 folders), 1880-1887 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
  - Financial matters (7 folders), 1888-1897 (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
    The 1893-94 folder includes a lengthy letter to the rector, et al. from Reverend Charles G. Adams of the St. Mark's Memorial Chapel concerning his apparent termination.
  - Financial matters (8 folders), 1898-1913 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    The 1899 folder includes several document concerning the search for a new rector at the time, leading to the selection of L.W. Batten.
  - Budget Committee and related documents, 1912-1917 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Supplementary folders: Financial matters (4 folders), 1840s-1890s, undated (Box 8, Folder 2-5)
  - Ladies' Auxiliary Missionary Society cash journal, 1875-1887 January (Box 1)
    Booklet also includes some loose financial documents concerning the Ladies Benevolent Society, Cutting Committee, and others.
  - Treasurer's Account Books (3), 1860 April-1907 March (Box 9, Item 5-7)
  - Bank account book (at Gallatin National Bank), 1882-1888 (Box 9, Item 1)
  - Rectory Fund books (2), 1899-1909 (Box 9, Item 2-3)
    One book records Rectory Fund receipts from 1899-1909. The second appears to be a record of bank deposits for the Fund for 1905-1908.
  - Check book stubs, 1876 February-1877 June (Box 9, Item 4)
  - Check book stubs, 1896 June-1899 June (Volume 6)
  - Cancelled checks, 1847-1889 (Box 10)
    Bundles of some checks for portions of some years: 1847, 1859, 1860, 1861, 1885-1890; and 1900-1901 for the Rectory Fund.
  - Tax bills, 1845-1888 (Box 10)
    Not all years here. Includes 1845, 1865, 1866, 1868, 1869, 1872, 1875, 1877, 1882, 1885, 1886, 1888.
  - Insurance policies, 1840s-1880s (Box 10)
    The 1840s policy is on the organ.
  - Deeds and leases (1 bundle) (RESTRICTED), 1809-1834 (Box 10)
    This bundle of documents is unprocessed and requires work by a processing archivist before use. Please allow an extra business day for processing before the date of anticipated use.
  - Deeds and leases (7 folders) (RESTRICTED), 1796-1917 (Box 11, Folder 1-7)
    The items in this box are unprocessed and require work by a processing archivist before use. Please allow an extra business day for processing before the date of anticipated use.
  - Pew rentals, deeds, etc. (5 folders), 1811-1915 (Box 8, Folder 7-11)
    There appear to be some burial vault agreements in these folders as well. The files include an 1891 report from the Committee on Pews & Cemeteries.
  - Annual report, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Series III. Other Administration Records, 1800-1944; .63 Linear feet in 2 document boxes
  This small series includes two sets of miscellaneous administrative documents, including drafts of vestry minutes; correspondence, including letters "declining the call" from 1800-1801, as well as others concerning calls to the pulpit or resignations; some printed material; various lists of interments, marriages, etc., and other material. Some financial documents are here also. More detailed summaries are noted in the container list.
  The series identifies two sets of documents. One, donated by St. Mark's, includes files not generally identified as those belonging to the church treasurer (which are in Series II). A second set was purchased by N-YHS from a manuscript dealer and kept together; these records appear to have been drafts and other working documents of the church clerk.
  - Various files (19 folders), 1800-1944 (Box 12, Folder 1-19)
    Includes a wide variety of documents including, among others, letters "declining call" (1800-1801); records of alms/contributions (1842-1883); reports of interments (1845-1850s); map of the cemetery (1852); vestry elections (1806, 1817, 1818); correspondence (1830s-1890s); documents concerning St. Mark's Memorial Chapel (1866-1945); pamphlets and other small print material; registry of marriages (1873-1874, 1877-1884); resignation of rector J.H. Rylance (1898) and subsequent call to L.H. Batten; miscellaneous documents re: St. Mark's communion cloth, 6th Street Mission, document lists, etc.
  - John W. Mitchell (Clerk) records, circa 1835-1845 (Box 13)
    Includes four folders of documents apparently maintained by John W. Mitchell. These include rough draft minutes of vestry meetings (1839-1842); Auditing Committee notes (circa 1841); some bills, correspondence, leases, records of pew rentals, and other documents. Many of the documents are in rough draft form.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    This set of files appear to have been purchased by N-YHS in 1972 from Gilman's rare book store.
- Series IV. Buildings Renovation and Restoration, 1966-2019; 44 Linear feet
  Biographical / Historical
  This series includes records related to the late 20th century preservation of the St. Mark's church building and, after devastating fires, the restoration of the church and rectory into the early 21st century. Following is a sketch of this history as it relates to the content of the series:
  The series generally starts in the late 1960s with the formation of the Preservation Youth Project (PYP) in 1968, initially as a summer jobs program and then an after-school work program for neighborhood youth. The project initially completed the restoration of the east and west graveyards before turning in 1975 to a long-range restoration of the interior and exterior of the church building itself. The Friends of St. Mark's was organized to financially support PYP, which in 1975 became a full-time work training program to work on the major renovation project, overseen by artisans and master craftspeople. This project was almost complete when on July 27, 1978, a fire broke out in the church, causing massive damage.
  Immediately after the fire, the Friends of St. Mark's re-organized as the Citizen's Committee to Save St. Mark's in order to raise funds towards the Church's restoration. The following year, in 1979, the structure for the receipt and disbursement of monies was formalized as the St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund thanks to a seed gift from LuEsther T. Mertz. Nevertheless the Citizen's Committee name was in common use on solicitations until the work was eventually completed in the mid-1980s. With the work again done by members of the Preservation Youth Project, the church was rededicated in 1983 and the work was fully completed in 1987.
  The Landmark Fund that was formed in 1979 had three goals: to restore the historic buildings and grounds of St. Mark's; to generate an endowment for its future care and preservation; and to strengthen the public use of St. Mark's by fostering its innovative arts and community projects. Not long after the completion of the church restoration, another fire ravaged the historic rectory in 1988. This building was a landmark, designed by architect Ernest Flagg in 1900. Again, the Landmark Fund and the PYP were engaged in the restoration. Work was completed on the exterior, but funding could not be obtained to restore the interior for its former use as a rectory. In 1997, the Landmark Fund secured a commitment from the LuEsther T. Mertz Charitable Trust to fund the interior restoration provided that the Fund could develop an appropriate, mission-related and financially sustainable adaptive re-use for the building. This resulted in the formation of the Neighborhood Preservation Center (NPC), which opened in 1999.
  The NPC provided office space for the Landmark Fund, the Greenwich Village Society for Historic Preservation, and the Historic Districts Council, as well as offering public meeting spaces, temporary office space to community organizations, and research resources for preservation efforts. The NPC was managed by the Landmark Fund under a 20 year agreement with St. Mark's. With the expiration of that agreement in 2019, management of the former rectory reverted to St. Mark's and the Landmark Fund closed down, turning its records over to the church. The NPC continues to exist, now as a standalone 501(c)3 organization.
  (The above note was based on information from the websites of St. Mark's, the New York Preservation Archive Project, and the Neighborhood Preservation Center; documents in the collection; and notes from an earlier finding aid prepared at the Landmark Fund.)
  The series includes records related to the restoration work on the church and rectory, including Preservation Youth Project (PYP) administrative records, correspondence and other documents regarding suppliers and other service providers, proposals, and the like. There are extensive records related to the funding for these projects, including grant proposals, budgets, financial reports, fundraising solicitations, and the like. Governance and administration of the St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund is well documented with Fund trustee minutes, audit/financial reports, IRS Form 990s, investment account statements, and some detailed transactional accounting records. There are many photographs, including slides and albums, documenting the fire damage, Preservation Youth Project restoration efforts from the 1970s and forward, and events in the 1980s, such as the visit of Queen Beatrix of the Netherlands.
  The series includes two subseries of records that span the late 1960s to 2019 and encompass the interrelated initiatives underlying the restorations of St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery and its rectory building. The records are from mixed sources. Certain of the records were created by the St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund (1979-2019). To those over time were added records from former Fund officials during the 2010s, including presidents Georgia Delano, Nicholas Fish, and Stephen Facey. Facey, a former St. Mark's Parish Administrator was an organizer of the Preservation Youth Project and several of the files came from his office. By 2019 when the Landmark Fund closed, all these records were maintained in one set of files within that office. However, with the close and subsequent donation to New-York Historical, St. Mark's identified the appropriate split of records between those generated by the Landmark Fund and those more properly viewed as records of the church. This split is represented by the two subseries and the physical separation of the material, while retaining the close topical relationship here.
  Subseries IV.A. St. Mark's Church Preservation Youth Project and Other Restoration Records
  Subseries IV.B. St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund
  Within each subseries, the files remain as arranged when they arrived at N-YHS. The office files remain in their original folders with original labeling. These original folders include references to drawer, box, and folder numbers; these refer to the files as they were found and inventoried in the Landmark Fund offices from 2015-19.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The material in this series is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
  Related Materials
  NYHS holds the records of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland, which includes documents related to the Society's installation in 1903 of the Peter Stuyvesant stained glass window above his burial vault and their support for the window's restoration circa 2010.
  - Subseries IV.A. St. Mark's Church Preservation Youth Project and Other Restoration Records, 1966-2012; 18 Linear feet
    The subseries includes office files and photographs primarily related to the Preservation Youth Project (PYP) from its earliest formation in the late 1960s through its restoration work into the 1990s. These files include grant proposals, work plans and budgets, fundraising efforts, and participant records. There are also publicity materials about the PYP and its work, as well as the major fires that led to continued restoration work by the PYP. Supplier and contractor estimates and proposals for various aspects of the churchyard and later church work are in these files.
    These files also hold various other photographs from the 1970s-2004, related both to some events at St. Mark's and the renovation of the rectory and re-opening as the Neighborhood Preservation Center, as well as some files related to the Landmark Fund's efforts, though these are principally in the following subseries.
    With perhaps only minor changes, the files are arranged as delivered to N-YHS, which is generally with office files followed by photographs and other graphic material.
    - Files: Publicity; Repairs, 1970s-1999 (Offsite-box 14)